Spectacular, isn't it?
Probably! What is it?
I've created a simulation
of the entire universe!
Oh! In that case, it stinks.
I keep forgetting, Professor.
Are we in the entire universe?
Why, naturally!
Good news, everyone!
We've got a delivery!
But first, roll call!
Leela? 3-PIXEL LEELA: Here.
- Fry?
- Present!
- Scruffy?
- Yep.
- Hermes?
- Check.
Bender?
Bite
my shiny middle pixel!
- Amy?
- Shmobviously.
And the rest.
Hooray! I'm
an unnamed member of the group!
That's amazing, Professor!
How'd you make it so crummy?
It wasn't easy. Even to
achieve this level of realism
requires vast amounts
of computing power.
My Simputron uses
more electricity
than 100 bug zappers.
Which reminds me, I had
to unplug our bug zappers.
- Ow!
- Got him!
The mosquito is still alive.
There's a mosquito?
Listen up, threeple!
Today, you'll be delivering
this package to Space Italy.
Space Italy?
I know, it's an
embarrassingly lazy name.
But when you're creating an
entire universe from scratch,
you can't make up a believable
name for everything.
Sometimes, you just have
to go with "Space Italy"
or "the Robot Planet"
or "Dr. Zoidberg."
Preposterous.
Wow, Space Italy!
You delivering that
package, Bender?
Up all
those steps? No grazie.
I'll just chuck it into
Trevi Fountain for good luck.
Ooh!
Papa pia!
He hit-a the Space Pope!
You're under
arrest for-a bonking His Holiness.
I tell-a
you, this-a Planet Express company
is a real two-bit operation, eh?
More
like three!
So, um,
as long as we're here,
wanna see the sights?
When
in Space Rome...
Michelangelo's
David! So lifelike!
Jeez,
Dave! Get a fig leaf!
3-PIXEL GONDOLIER
La la la!
La la la...
I just can't
understand how it doesn't fall dow...
Let me
give you a han...
Oh, mama, they're goin' at
it like two packs of gum!
Bender, give us
a little privacy.
Aw...
So, do those people
in the casserole
know they're in a simulation,
or do they think
that they're real?
Of course, they
think they're real.
To them, the rules
of my software
are just their laws of physics.
But, we think we're real.
Couldn't our universe
also be a simulation?
Absolutely
not! No chance.
The very idea is preposterous!
- How can you be so sure?
Because it's
computationally impossible!
For example, every
atom in the universe
is affected whenever
one little thing moves.
Like my ass?
Oh yeah! Come on!
That's a
perfect example, Bender,
and some pretty decent
twerking.
My software can't possibly
compute the gravitational changes
between Bender's ass and
every other particle,
so I had to have the information
travel outward gradually,
at a fixed speed.
Like the speed of
light in our universe?
Right!
Oh, fuff. That's
just a coincidence.
I had to cut other corners, too.
I mean, my simulation
doesn't even keep track
of exactly where everything is.
Takin' all bets!
Find the ball, win
me not punching you!
My last $5
on cup number one!
In fact, make it my last $10!
Another convenient example.
My lazy software wouldn't even
decide which cup the ball's in
until someone actually looked
at it.
Until then, it's
just sort of in both.
So your programming shortcut
is like quantum
mechanics in our world?
Exactly like that!
Hm, interesting.
I guess what I'm
trying to say is
our universe is probably
also a simulation.
But that's the exact opposite
of what you said one minute ago!
New evidence was presented
and I changed my mind.
I'm a scientist, not a...
- Idiot?
- Politician.
Man. Imagine how
awful it would be
to find out your whole
personality was just simulated,
like Bender's.
Whuzzulated? Like whozer's?
I just mean you're an
artificial intelligence, Bender.
Like the people in the
Professor's simulation.
- Artificial?
- Uh-huh. Yep.
Why'd you have to tell me?
You just ruined my life!
My big fat fake life!
You're a walking bucket!
How can you say I'm not real?!
If you prick me, do I not bleed?
Okay, that was a bad example!
Ow! I'm bleeding!
- Showoff.
- There, there, Bender.
You're as real as any of us.
The philosopher
René Descartes said,
"I think, therefore I am."
Can you think?
- I don't think so!
I think I might not
be able to think!
Anyway, it was a
fun little universe,
but we're looking at a
Godzilla-sized electric bill.
It's time to shut it down.
But, you can't
just turn them off!
That would be like
turning me off!
Good idea! That'll
save even more power!
But we'll start with them.
No...
The plug is stuck.
Or maybe
I'm just extraordinarily weak.
That is a possibility.
Oh, bother. I'll just keep the
simulation running a little longer.
Thanks,
Professor!
Bender, how were you leaping
through the air that entire time?
I wasn't! My first
leap missed by a mile,
so I leapt again.
But I never stopped
screaming for a second!
I feel like I've been
in existence for a while now, Leela.
So it's time I set
myself a life's goal.
That's a great idea!
I'll be quiet and let you think.
And I'll turn on the
TV to drown out any distracting noises.
That's it!
I found my life's goal!
I, Philip J. Fry, hereby pledge
to watch every TV
show ever made.
Oh Lord.
That orange guy sure is dumb.
These innocent bit
bags may be artificial,
like me,
but they don't know that!
They deserve the same respect
as any other living creature.
Except clams!
To hell with clams!
I'm telling you they're
nothing but ones and zeros!
They're no more alive
than the number 10101.
She was my aunt!
Professor, I think
Bender might be right.
No, you don't!
I mean, we're nothing
more than atoms, right?
But, somehow, we are more.
Unlike clams!
Professor, I will now ask
of you a solemn promise.
Now, the feet.
- Forget the feet!
Alright, whatever.
Why are we in a
robot strip club?
Because we had to
do this in a place
that's meaningful to me!
Bender!
Here you go, hun.
- Keep the change, toots.
- Ow!
Let the solemn ceremony begin.
Professor, you created a world
of conscious living beings,
so now you're
responsible for them.
I want you to swear you'll
do everything in your power
to keep them alive.
I barely make any effort
to keep myself alive.
Oof!
- Professor!
And you'll never let them
know they're not real! Never!
So they won't have to go
through what I'm going through!
I swear nothing!
I said swear it!
Very well. I swear it.
But the amount of electricity...
Why, we'd basically need our
own hydroelectric generator.
I really don't think
there's any possible...
Eureka!
As you all know, I do my
best thinking on the toilet.
We know! Stop telling us!
I didn't even have to go.
I was just sitting here,
wiling away a Sunday afternoon,
when suddenly, it hit me!
A new source of electricity!
Would you care to tell us
about it... in another room?
No!
According to these old maps,
which I use in lieu
of toilet paper...
Ew!
The main New New York sewer line
runs directly under
Planet Express.
We'll simply
drill into the pipe,
drop this turbine
into the torrent,
and voila! Free clean power!
- Clean?
- Oh my, no.
We're approaching
the main pipeline.
Can you imagine the quantity of
sewage running through there?
Yes!
Contact in four! Three!
Number two!
Let's rarely speak
of that again.
This should generate enough power
to keep the simulation running.
And it's substantially
higher resolution!
Let's see how my guys are doing.
Good news, everyone!
We have a delivery
to the King of Space.
Aw, they're so cute!
Now I care about them!
Happy, Bender? We saved
your little friends.
I sure did.
In other news,
I've made a huge breakthrough!
- What is it, Professor?
- No, him.
- After many sleepless nights
and an equal number of
glorious sleep-filled days,
I've completed my
greatest achievement!
A simulation of our
entire universe!
Good news, everyone!
We have a delivery
to Space Italy!
Sweet facsimile of Space Italy!
A simulation...
Within a simulation!?
Where does it all end?
- Hopefully there.
Already my head hurts.
Professor, if you can make
a whole simulated universe,
isn't it possible
that our own universe
is also a simulation?
Absolutely not!
You sound like a
stoned freshman!
I mean, what if our laws of
physics are just the computer code
of some big brilliant
professor playing god up there?
Nailed it!
Hm. Quantum mechanics
is pretty ridiculous,
but it's a moot point.
Even if we are living
in a simulation,
there's no possible
way of knowing.
Yes?
Oh, nothing. I just had
a loogie in my throat.
Possibly a simulated
loogie.
What's that? A
g-g-g-grid overload?
My simulation is drawing a
lot of power for some reason.
Ah! It appears two black
holes just collided in there.
Can you imagine how complex
that computation is?
The Simputron is really
straining to keep up.
Oh, my glorsh!
Maybe there is a way to find
out if we live in a simulation.
Well, I doubt that.
Double doubt it!
If our universe is a simulation,
then it's running on some
kind of computer, right?
I'm with you so far.
Actually, I'm not. Is
this about a new soda?
Suppose we made something
happen that was impossible
for that big
computer to simulate.
It would overload!
Exactly!
Cool! And then what?
I don't know! Probably stuff
would pixelate and look weird!
The laws of physics would fail!
Like playing a new video game on
a crummy underpowered game system!
Precisely!
That my cheapskate
grandma got me.
Some phenomena are
so wildly complex
that they'd be impossible
for any computer to simulate.
For example, a
collapsing magnetic star
or magnetar.
But such an event might not
happen for millions of years.
But, what if we intentionally
caused a magnetar to collapse?
Then, we could just watch and
see if the universe glitches out.
Of course! And we'd
know once and for all
if we're living in a simulation.
Although, I'm not sure I
wanna know the answer to that.
Me neither. I like resting
secure in the knowledge
that I'm the real deal.
Guess
again, loser.
Let's put it to a vote.
Who here wants to test if
we're living in a simulation?
And who would rather continue
living in shameful ignorance?
That one!
You all voted for two things.
Honestly. I wanna know if I'm
not living in a simulation,
but not if I am.
Does that make sense?
Surprisingly, yes. Let's
just forget about it.
Although, now we're
always gonna be wondering.
Let's just go.
Uh-oh. Not good.
Not good at all.
My half-baked software
absolutely will not be able
to simulate a
collapsing magnetar.
Oh, I never should
have outsourced it
to that Indian middle schooler.
But, the simulations will
find out they're simulations!
You swore a strip club oath
that would never happen.
Alas, there'll be
no hiding the truth
when they see that
magnetar glitching out
like a big flaming
ball of Microsoft Word.
Well, if they're
gonna find out anyway,
I should be the
one to tell them.
I'm the only one who
truly understands!
Plus, I like
delivering bad news.
Actually, that
might be possible.
Since you're basically
just software
in a greasy wad of
aluminum foil...
Aw...
I could extract your
programming, compress it,
and inject it into
Simulated Bender.
You'd take his place
in the simulated world.
But what would happen to him?
He'd be pushed through
to the sub-simulation.
And that Bender?
It's Benders all the way down.
Alright. I'm going in.
I must warn you, Bender.
It'll be a one-way trip.
There's no way of returning.
That's okay. I don't
wanna live in a world
where I'm less real
than everyone else.
Those are my people in there,
in Baloney Town.
Ooh!
In a few minutes,
you should reboot
in the simulated world
as Simulated Bender.
Or you might die.
Goodbye,
precious friends and coworkers.
Goodbye, sewage-stained
floor tiles.
Goodbye, Zoidberg.
How will I go on without you?
I'll get a broom.
Holding outside magnetar
implosion range.
We'll be safe at this distance,
even if, God forbid, we're real.
Then it's time to put
reality to the test.
- I'm scared!
- I am, too.
But it's actually
kind of beautiful.
Would it be any less
beautiful if it weren't real?
And we weren't real?
We'll find out soon enough.
Begin monopole bombardment!
You okay, buddy?
No!
Probably a bad clam.
I think I'm gonna reboot!
Oh...
Where... Where am I?
You're right here, Bender.
Just outside magnetar
implosion range.
Oh... Right.
Baloney Town.
Guys? I have
something to tell you,
and it'll be the
hardest bad news
I've ever had the
pleasure of delivering.
Shush, Bender! We're
about to find out
if we're living in a simulation!
Right... It-it's
about that. See...
I've been thinking about
that, too, actually.
And you wanna know what I think?
- Do I!
- I think it makes no difference at all.
Either way, the laws of the
universe are way beyond our control.
So, what can we do?
We just make the best of it.
I don't know what we're about
to see, Leela, but I love you.
Now and forever.
And that much is real,
even if we're not.
Hm... The dummy's right.
I feel, therefore I am.
It doesn't matter if I'm real?
Not one bit.
So what did you
wanna tell us, robot?
Just... thank you!
That's robots for you.
Now, let's sit back
and enjoy the show.
Oh, lordy-loo. The
magnetar is about to pop!
How's the Simputron holding up?
Processor overload!
The cooling fan's on fire!
Whoa!
Pull the plug! Stop the simulation!
No! Bender's in there!
There's no choice. This building's
about to go up in smoke,
and I've got doomsday devices
hidden in every nook and cranny.
I'm sorry, buddy.
I know you can't hear me,
but we tried our best.
At least you got to
go out with dignity.
Rebooting.
Where... Where am I?
Right here, in the universe.
Oh... I had to come
tell you something...
Bender? How did you possibly
manage to come back?
Don't be rude, Professor,
Bender was speaking first.
What did you wanna
tell us, robot?
It's just that...
I know how to save
the simulation.
Oh, please. There's
no possible...
Eureka!
I made the change you
suggested, Bender.
Although it took a lot of
toilet time to fully comprehend.
We won't need
nearly so much power
now that I've under-clocked
the processor.
But, won't the
simulation run slower?
Oh, much slower.
Are we talking regular
slow or bureaucrat slow?
Infinitely slower than that.
So they'll be in, like, a coma?
Oh my, no!
They'll never notice
any difference.
But while they live out
one second of their lives,
years, if not centuries,
will pass for us.
Aw, then I guess we won't
get to spy on them anymore.
Spy all you like.
But it's about to get
very, very boring.
Not for them.
Pixels...
To make it real, really real
She says
You just have to be here
rock guitar riff
On this satellite
Satellite
Had to be here
On this satellite
Satellite
Had to be here
On this satellite
Song slowly fades
electronic distortion
soft, orchestral
music playing